[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
Lynn it's Frank de Freitas
that's okay
I'm doing great how are you fine you
know for an old
I go to your website and I read all
kinds of incredible stuff I mean I mean
you're so brilliant you really are free
all right we can stop that now no I'm
serious I I uh I really do that it's
comforting
the day I was thinking about late
iode lasers
um and uh your stuff is still still out
you're still doing Holograms right oh
absolutely yeah I have someone coming in
tomorrow
coming up from Florida for a workshop
they're visiting relatives in
Philadelphia so they're going to drive
up to Allentown for a workshop tomorrow
did you ever
did you ever consider a
using a palm or plate I don't know if
you can buy the resin from DuPont
whether they sell it to the public or
they just keep it in house no I wouldn't
have the power or the wavelength right
now to do that I don't believe I do have
an argon laser here now oh you do yeah
wow
I got it from someone else and I still
have to get it hooked up because it
needs the 220 triple phase and like two
and a half gallons of water a minute
knock the neighborhood out you know
it's a power failure in the winter time
and it's not snow it's Frank de France
Hey listen I miss making Holograms so
much but
um the only thing that's kept me going
especially when I got some of my sight
back I saw you after I got my sight back
didn't I it's been a couple years it
might have been 2001 2002 but that's a
long time right and it's just
appropriate that you call now because
all of a sudden
I realize there's something
the lens implant
yeah well the one eye I'm using the lens
implant seems to have torn loose
internally and they're going to have to
take it out and put another one in I'm
going in for surgery on the 2nd of
November oh I hope everything works out
all right for you because in an implant
when after it's uncurled it's got
Springs on it to hold it in place so hey
it's one thing to have an opera one
operation
too the first you got
the building then put another one up so
it's the anesthesia I guess I should be
worried about you know as you get older
how old are you now
I'm 72 Frank no kidding why don't you
tell the listeners how you got started
with holography that was way back in the
60s wasn't it
uh yeah didn't you travel up to Canada
or something yeah well what happened I
died
I read somewhere first of all I read
details about holography in the current
magazines like Scientific American
things uh photography by laser I think
there was a big
but when I realized that the 67 Expo
advertised that they had a hologram on
display or several Holograms I just
decided to go I think it was um earlier
late September because it was cold on
the road and I just drove straight to
Canada from work I left work one day
walked out of school
got in the car and
long ride up to uh uh let me see it was
uh held in uh was it Montreal yeah at
some point I was doing 90 miles an hour
on this open Highway
and uh but when I got there I found out
that the everything was on strike all
the public transportation
and it was cold I mean it really wasn't
what I expected but um I went late at
night and I ran over to the booth where
uh the map said the Hologram was and the
lights were out
oh no and I couldn't see anything there
was nothing to see
because the Hologram was on display like
an outdoor kiosk yeah it wasn't like you
were an indoor building but
I still had a great time I had my 3D
camera with me and uh
after many many hours
you know there are a lot of mythical
Labyrinth
and I saw the Minotaur and matter of
fact I took 3D pictures of him because I
carried a tripod the sculpture oh okay
and I was doing time exposures you know
I'm talking about minutes and
can and covering it with a hat I bought
because I didn't want to touch the
camera lens came out razor sharp in
three days and
um we did a lot of 3D work didn't you
with photography too you know recently
in the last few years I was able to buy
a scanner and one of the reasons I want
my computer is really down numb the Dell
seems to have died I don't hear the hard
drive running I need a new computer yeah
but one of the reasons that uh I wanted
that I figured if I could put
on both sides both stereo images
in the computer I could reformat that
them as an analoglyph and I I did I
experimenting with that okay and that
way just anybody with a written blue
pair of paper glasses could see the
things I had done in 3D including my
grandkids oh and you were going to put
them on a web page I guess right yeah
yeah do you have that web page finished
no
it's crazy and now with this Vision
thing which is the last thing I
envisioned I'm just struggling to stay
afloat Frank
because it's hard without help you know
living alone you've always lived with
somebody yeah and you're surround
ER family
it's really hard when you uh I'm sorry
I'm surrounded by my own multiple
personalities
[Laughter]
no no you're a resource
yeah I remember you coming down for my
mother's uh funeral yeah I mean you
always get around where you want to get
Frank I I really you're fabulous how do
you know Frank me I just turned 50. oh
my God you're just a baby cake just a
baby cake hold on a second
[Music]
that's the uh
that's the weather alert
was it going to tell you sunshine is
coming out yes the sun's coming out
I miss being in the basement
yeah why don't you tell listeners about
your involvement with the Franklin
Institute and Central High School too
well
I had gone to Central as a young kid
wasn't doing well and I transferred out
and eventually graduated from Northeast
so it was strange to get back to Central
but
um
and I'll show you what age does for you
what was the there's no question
that's all right I was reading I was
reading about the Franklin Institute
holography program yeah I was reading an
email the inquire
D and uh they pointed out that the
Franco Institute had gotten a grant and
they were gonna they were going to offer
holography classes
and what what year was this
I'm guessing it was it would had to be
between
um
it had to be 76 77. somewhere in there
hold up and I I think
I think
Dan Goldwater was the head of the
science curriculum office down there he
was very nice
and uh Charles Penniman
who was a minister he was also involved
involved and they told me that there
were workshops and I don't remember
Scott's last name do you remember nimsel
yeah
house
I've been getting to know him he's a
very nice fellow Scott
uh in getting to know Scott nimsoff I
realized his father was a big shot a
vice president
of a major corporation yeah Borden Foods
I think
it was true
[Music]
and that's why Scott had a a place to go
I think Scott went to Brown University
yeah he worked with Harry cast and
silver up there I believe oh yeah okay
okay and he was very nice he was kind of
protective you know it's a
if you're a major if if you have a craft
uh you kind of want to protect it like
the original labor unions because if
everybody can do it you lose your uh you
lose your specialty
and I realized that too because at the
time that I discovered the holography
workshops I was
helping start up the gifted program in
the city of Philadelphia and
so I was fascinated I couldn't wait when
they called me and told me that I could
uh participate in the program I used to
rush down there and Scott used to do
show you how to make a hologram but
particularly by volunteering to spend
time in the labs you really learned
by trial and error how to how to make a
hologram well that was a pretty good lab
down there too wasn't it it was
marvelous because it had a um I think it
was a nine by twelve yeah it had to be a
9 by 12 isolation tape
that came from what's that big company
uh Newport Newport in California and
most of the equipment on the table
there was a large laser
a new one but uh Penniman had rebuilt it
if I remember
yeah it was at spectrophysics 125 right
the special room was set aside you you
could lose your hologram
people would run up and down the
stairwell next to the uh next to the lab
but I love being in there and eventually
I figured out pretty much on my own how
to make a transmission hologram and that
became I mean I used to leave
to leave work which is school on a
Friday and you could book a uh I say
think a three or four hour
um
amount of time in the lab where you
could work and other people could
I became friendly believe it or not
because the Institute closed up at five
o'clock there was a guard and they used
to hire guards from a service
and I became very friendly with this one
guard and he would just let me in and
he'd let me wait or sit or whatever I
used to live in the lab all weekend
because very few people the novelty wore
off and very few people uh really took
advantage
the lab but I found it I found it
fascinating in the the first time that I
made a magical and high quality 4x5
hologram
dancing and there was nobody to watch
uh it was just it was superb so
sometimes I used to be in there all
weekend because I'd wait if nobody
showed up the guard I remember his first
name was Henry he was he was marvelous
and uh instead of going home I would
stay eventually I even used to date
and I found out he would let the other
person in and
strange to be
used to be Henry and myself in the whole
Institute so you are you saying you
would take your date to the Franklin
Institute and the lifography lab yeah
come to the door and Henry would say
he's down in the lab
he called down and I say it's okay you
can let her down and uh
and I can I can prove it one of the
women is still alive
there was a photo booth there you know
Polaroid photo booth when they first
became popular yeah you put a dollar in
and you take photos
but it it it it was superb and
eventually
chaos
the gifted program was going nowhere and
one day when they had a show and uh I
was the science person in the gifted
program I had an idea that I could take
some of the money that was being unused
when they they were going to close up
the lab and Charles Penniman helped me
write a letter and we rented we we paid
Newport to keep the
and I put out a notice in the in all the
Philadelphia schools that anybody that
was
that was in coming to the lab they'd
have to come on their own I couldn't
provide transportation that was the big
themselves you know they're only kids
yeah but eventually they started coming
and we had a lab and we the kids made
Holograms and it was never it never
received any recognition like they did
up in Boston or anywhere else because
Philadelphia is a strange town uh they
knew I was doing Holograms yeah uh
uh and some of the parents were one
one of the parents of a girl she was she
was a brilliant mathematician
um she while she was in high school
the girls we were sending her to pen
for advanced math and uh she used to
explain some of the math that I couldn't
understand but she had to leave the
program because one of the teachers told
her mother she could go blind working in
a lab with laser lasers oh no you know
you're running an unbelievable
but her dad was the one he was a lawyer
he wrote he wrote the uh release that I
sent out to all the
that their parents agreed that they
could come to the lab and I was very
careful to make sure no one ever got
hurt you know it was really safety being
a teacher and watching kids was uh was
good training because I
10 15 kids in the lab with it which is a
lot first of all you don't want any body
movement that was the hardest part
but uh one interesting thing happened
Scott nems
go off on vacation One Summer and
he was teaching a class of adults and
there was nobody to teach it and I said
to Charlie Charlie Penniman I would be
glad to teach it if you allow me I don't
have his expertise and I ended up
teaching that class and one of the
members of the board of directors of the
Franklin Institute was in that
two of them so that was a big a Big
Thrill being
at Holograms and working with adults it
was just the marvelous time I mean
some people want to go to Paris
and want to go to Russia
I just wanted to get to the lab and and
work on that
isolation table it was fabulous yeah
they were years before I got involved I
I saw my first show down at the Walnut
Street Theater in 76. I still have the
flyer from that show do you have that
yeah I had a poster and I have no idea
what I did with the poster I'm pretty
sure they have that flyer
um yeah and what about was um Ken
dunkley and Doug Miller involved with
that at all Doug Miller
I think he entered one of the workshops
because they run different workshops
depending on the funding they got
Ken dunkley had already been a
holographer
he um
he was tied in with the Franklin
Institute I still remember that remember
that face he did with
oh yeah it's classic That's a classic
hologram and he would give lectures to
uh the rest of us about that I mean he
was brilliant and I remember the
tri-color Holograms when they first
started showing them when they were
swelling things with triathanol I mean
oh yeah I love doing that uh oh you you
became an expert at that well I wouldn't
say an expert but I enjoyed doing it
I'll have you wanna if you wanted
toxicity just see Frank he'll Supply it
you know I'm very lucky with all the
chemicals because we all you know we all
get sloppy we have our hands in all the
chemistry
oh yeah as a kid my father was a
watchmaker and he sent me the cleaning
clocks
I was immersed in Benzene which is a
carcinogenic hydrocarbon by today's
standards
I I'm just amazed that uh
I'm here well in the early days I used
the Mercure chloride bleach in the
parabenzoquinone and even the bromine oh
well that's violence which violent
how to clear the house out one time with
it I once I once remember in college we
used to manufacture probably bromine in
the chem lab and it was in the
summertime and we were cooling the
condensate with
uh test tubes to pack to nice
and one of the test tubes fell and broke
and there was uh was it was brutal we
had eye injuries and everything else so
you know these things that we work with
are pretty pretty toxic yeah John a
little bit
but I
I really never had a chance to finish in
the labs you know they closed the labs
down
and
I kept I kept working you know I kept
teaching holography as you remember at
the Franklin Institute as a small
workshop and even at Weidner College
but when plates became and I built the
table here in the living room but his
plates
uh everything became you know less
accessible yeah and it slowly faded away
and I had a wonderful I used to
program
most teachers would ask them you know
their backgrounds I would ask what's
your father do what your grandfather do
and they got to know it I could hear the
kids mumbling in the background they
would say listen to what he's going to
ask them I was looking for a machinist
oh okay and I found one oh yeah okay and
he helped me he helped me formulate all
those parts that you saw how to scrap
metals do you still have those I
have those
that's why I was thinking of building a
laser diode
and uh because I still have a laser I
think it'll fire up or I would buy him a
diode laser and supervise it because you
know I how much I love the the Holograms
well I'll tell you what next time I'm
down in Philadelphia I'll stop by and
I'll bring one of the shoebox allography
books a box of plates and and the small
laser pointers for him to work with
how's that that's fabulous Frank I'll
bring it down I know where you're at
you're still I won't give the street
address but the number's still 7227
right yes yes yeah
you're not going to broadcast this silly
conversation are you oh yeah I'm going
to edit it down a little bit
it has nothing of value well it's got
some history to it I mean a lot of the
people that will be listening to this
show many of them weren't even born when
uh
you're talking about some of the things
that you did you know in the 60s I would
spend hours with a pencil and a piece of
paper just trying to draw
what scientific instruments and plate
holders and uh
and and pointers and so forth uh you
know the uh remember we used to move the
panel
in Hawaii axis oh yeah so that if I
could get a hold of uh
Clarence
and he had time in his shop he would
take scraps of metal and work with them
and then bring me what he had made and
said will this work and we said well
let's rework it this way and that's
where all the equipment came from that
you saw eventually yeah I was I was
really very fascinated that he would
help me do
and at Central High School I finally was
able to clean out
a roach infested room it took me months
I mean it's a horrible experience
I'm not kidding about the roaches
and as soon as I got it cleaned out and
it was able to start
the star table in there because I wanted
to do holography with
the kids
They confiscated it for music storage
instruments
okay so holography never got going
isn't that something well that's because
you know the the administration didn't
think it would have any value yeah and
it was probably oh I don't know a lot of
its politics and and funding and things
of that nature well I they I didn't ask
them for anything see I was supplying
all the funding and all the equipment
okay all I needed was a physical
but it probably wasn't making them any
money they probably found some way of
having the band well I wasn't a favorite
on the list yeah and the band that's the
politics part yeah you know I
you know the other principle
I was at a school remember I said all
the junior high school kids came from
all over the city yeah that principle
let me not come in that day but report
to the Franklin Institute said I was in
his Bell you know I call in that I'm in
the building and Charles Penniman uh and
Dan Dan Goldwater they were they were
marvelous they used to wonder why aren't
you here teaching science because the
other teachers would bring classes in
and they do little trivial experiments
like batteries involved those things
that you
the teachers rooms yeah but education
hasn't changed much I keep thinking I
keep hearing about how things are going
to get better in education
probably worse than when I store I store
it because it first of all it takes it
takes a family to bring a kid to school
and say sit here and learn and I used to
end up screaming at my kids because it
didn't matter
after many years of teaching whether I
gave a test
on any given day I would give any kid
any test he wanted
a day he won
he won it takes forever and then I had
retests you could take it's learning the
material is important but just let the
kid learn in his own time yeah and I
remember screaming do you want to work
at a Burger King or do you want to own
one
Frank do you have a call coming in yeah
hold on a second just one second
all right well say goodbye to the
listeners listen
I'm I'm very honored to be able to speak
to any to my old friend Frank all right
I really mean that that's it's been a
terrific treat and uh Frank I'm looking
forward to seeing you and talking about
lots of things listen Frank
down could you bring
three-dimensional portrait Holograms are
the little mini portraits yeah I'll
bring it down I would love to see one
while I can all right thanks Frank all
right I'll talk to you soon what a treat
talking to you thanks Frank all right
bye bye-bye